[SPEAKER_03]: You may begin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Come in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm ###.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm a social worker.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_02]: May I get your name?
[SPEAKER_02]: Judy Marshall.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So Jamie Marshall was brought to the emergency room today.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's my husband.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's your husband.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so can you talk to me a little bit about what happened today?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, this morning we were cleaning out the garage because it's such a nice day and he started having problems breathing and used his inhaler a couple of times and
[SPEAKER_02]: And then he kept sweeping, and then a little bit later, half an hour later, he had to use it again because he was really having trouble breathing more so than I've ever seen him.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I decided to call 911, so I did that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he, you know, they brought him in with the ambulance, by ambulance.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I followed in the car because this has happened before.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm assuming that I can take him home pretty soon.
[SPEAKER_02]: So do you know?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you know how he is?
[SPEAKER_02]: How's he doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: So he was brought in, as you know, like with the breathing issues.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so the physicians are working with him now to try and get him stabilized and to, you know, ensure that his breathing gets back to a normal state.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, good.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so they're just working a little bit right now on him and with him.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there's a care team.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so the doctor will have some updates shortly and then I can,
[SPEAKER_02]: help you with that as well, and we can talk about that as we get done.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so we're working with him right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good, good, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a relief.
[SPEAKER_02]: I thought maybe something was wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, so we'll have some more updates coming up, and so we'll be able to talk a little bit more about it once we know more.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so there were some cardiac
[SPEAKER_02]: complications, and so they're working with that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so the doctor will be able to speak in more detail about that, just in terms of like a clinical perspective and their trajectory moving forward.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so you don't know any more than that?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, just that they're working on, you know, stabilizing him and getting the breathing under control and some of the cardiac complications as well stabilized, so yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You did the right thing by calling 9-1-1 when you noticed that something was amiss this morning.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we'll just wait to see what the next update is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But do you have any other questions for me?
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't think of anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you're a social worker, is that what you said?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I'm a social worker and I work here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Michigan Medicine.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't think of anything, I'll just wait until the doctor comes so I can take him home.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so we'll definitely wait for those updates and see from there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I'll come back in with the doctor.
[SPEAKER_02]: But is there anything that you think that we should know about that we haven't discussed regarding what happened this morning?
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't think of anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said, this has happened before.
[SPEAKER_02]: The first time I brought him in myself, but then I thought, oh, I better call 911 because he was really having trouble.
[SPEAKER_02]: And is there anyone that would be coming in, support person or any other family member or friend?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, now that you ask, actually I called Betsy, and she'll be here maybe half an hour.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And who's Betsy?
[SPEAKER_02]: She's our daughter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, Betsy's daughter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and she's...
[SPEAKER_02]: She's coming in from Michigan State.
[SPEAKER_02]: She's at school there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But she had kind of a light day, so I thought I'll call her, and then she can be there when her dad gets home.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So she should be here maybe half an hour or so.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, that's good.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so if she's not here when the doctor comes back, I'll come back in and we'll do additional updates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Time is up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right, that sounds good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: See you soon, I hope.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: You may begin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Come in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hello.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mrs. Marshall?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: My name is Dr. Kraft.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was one of the physicians taking care of your husband, Jamie.
[SPEAKER_02]: How's he doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I take him home yet?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I understand your daughter is on her way as well?
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, that's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: She's coming from Michigan State.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it okay if we start talking without her?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you want to wait for her?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I think we can go ahead and fill her in when she gets here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you tell me a little bit about what happened before the Indians arrived?
[SPEAKER_02]: You mean this morning before he came in?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, as I told ###, we were cleaning the garage and it was kind of dusty and he was sweeping and had trouble breathing, so he went in and got his inhaler and took a couple puffs and then he went back to cleaning and moving some things and
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I noticed he was really having trouble breathing, and he tried a few more puffs of his inhaler, and it just didn't seem to work.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I thought, if this is getting kind of serious, I better call 911.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I did, and then the ambulance came and took him.
[SPEAKER_02]: But as I told ###, this has happened once or twice before, so I just decided to drive, and so I can just take him home when he's ready to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I've got my car here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unfortunately, I have some bad news.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when your husband came in, he was having a lot of difficulty breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so we gave him some medications.
[SPEAKER_01]: And despite the medications, he still continued to have quite some difficulty breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we put in a breathing tube to help with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: After putting in the breathing tube, he was still having some problems.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he went into what's called cardiac arrest.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means his heart wasn't pumping effectively.
[SPEAKER_01]: We gave him some more medication, and we started CPR on him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unfortunately, despite our best efforts, we were unsuccessful, and your husband, Jamie, died.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry for your loss.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm very sorry for your loss.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh my god.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't believe it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I should have called the ambulance earlier.
[SPEAKER_02]: You did the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't do anything wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: You did the right thing calling the ambulance and having them call you.
What?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you mind telling me what's going through your mind right now?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know how I'm going to tell Betsy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there someone else that we could call for you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Any other family member, friend, spiritual person?
[SPEAKER_02]: Also, I can be here with you to talk to her about that as well, to help you, if that would be helpful.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll be available to talk to your daughter as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know this is very overwhelming.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I have a Kleenex?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, did he suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, when we put breathing tube in, we sedated him and he was unconscious when he went into cardiac arrest, so I don't believe he was in any pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did he say anything?
[SPEAKER_01]: None.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can be very difficult.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's really shocking and unexpected, especially considering, you know, I mentioned this has happened before, and, you know, when we talked, you know, we were hoping for a different outcome, certainly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's very difficult.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a lot to take in at one time.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there's no one else that you want us to call for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the hospital also has people of all different faith traditions, if that's something that's important.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just want Beth to be here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: She'll be here soon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I know when she's here.
[SPEAKER_02]: So they'll let us know, and then we can bring her back.
[SPEAKER_02]: And again, if you'd like, we can be here to have that conversation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Would you do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: She might have questions.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't even know what.
[SPEAKER_02]: what you said about what you did, but... Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll be here.
[SPEAKER_02]: She'll want to know.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know she'll want to know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you like to see your husband one more time?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's he going to look like?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we can bring you and you can go see him.
[SPEAKER_01]: He looks okay right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I think I'll wait until Betsy comes, is that right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I know it's a lot to take in right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So something that we do have that we give individuals is this packet on next steps.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't feel pressured to look through it right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like what?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you mean next steps?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so planning.
[SPEAKER_02]: So after this, funeral arrangements and some tips on the grieving process and things like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, it's...
[SPEAKER_02]: lot of information and so just taking the time to you know look at it when you can so I'll just leave it with you and we could talk about it as well when Betsy gets here so that way all the information isn't on you only the two of you can support each other through this process okay I can arrange for you to have my
[SPEAKER_01]: contact information so that if you have any questions, even after today, you can reach me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll talk to you then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So any other questions or else?
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't think of anything right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I'm in shock.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is just overwhelming.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was such a good husband.
[SPEAKER_02]: And a good father.
[SPEAKER_02]: Betsy's just going to be heartbroken.
[SPEAKER_02]: But Julie, I'll just sit with you or you sit with you until she gets here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'd be happy to do so.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I'll just sit here and wait for her to come.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll let me know when she gets here, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll let you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a lot to take in, so understandably so.
[SPEAKER_02]: You did the right thing by calling the ambulance and getting him here as soon as you could.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know this is overwhelming, but please reach out if you need anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Five minutes remaining.
Amen.
[SPEAKER_04]: Time is up.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm putting all these, I'm shutting them all off and putting them on Firefox.
[SPEAKER_02]: Have you done this one yet?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Firefox.
[SPEAKER_02]: Firefox, Fire, whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Firefox.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, they are, but it comes right out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here's for social work.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thanks for switching things up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, internet keeps crashing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Internet Explorer.
[SPEAKER_02]: I did most of these.
[SPEAKER_00]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: That one's probably just .
[SPEAKER_02]: And when we put Firefox on it, whatever it is, it puts upgrades on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it only took a second.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me know what it keeps.
[SPEAKER_02]: If we get the same thing, then it's like a system glitch.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something's going on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I'm just going to start getting rid of the paper.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, so if they get a message.
[SPEAKER_02]: that says, try to go back.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't click the back button.
[SPEAKER_02]: Try to return.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's three options.
[SPEAKER_00]: One of them is try to return.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you click that, it takes you back to the completed one.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you click the back button, it goes back to that completed one.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you have to click using the option that says, try to return to the former page.
[SPEAKER_02]: Click that when it says that.
All these are changed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, just look at the browns when it's open.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry, I was coming to talk about the valuations.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
All right, so the paging is all set up, right?
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I think 1888.
So her name was ###.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, when I realized when she first came in, I'm ###, and I'm a social worker.
[SPEAKER_02]: I didn't even pay attention to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So how would patients who are sitting here waiting for news, bad news, remember that?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I asked her again, you know, who are you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I think that people don't pay attention to that, or I do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you?
[SPEAKER_02]: You're thinking, you're not thinking about who is she, what she do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I was a social worker, so I, they wouldn't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just assume.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I probably, what's the word, rating social workers more importantly than they mean.
That's funny.
[SPEAKER_01]: So yeah, it depends on the sophistication of the person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people might wonder, so what does the social worker do?
[SPEAKER_02]: What was her name, ###?
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, it wasn't ###.
[SPEAKER_02]: It wasn't ###.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, or is it, I wonder if that's a, we better clarify that, because I have Mandy up on my sheet, but I thought she said ###.
[SPEAKER_02]: She did.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so it's ###.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, you know, she's going by a different name.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, or maybe, I heard, I heard, um,
[SPEAKER_02]: Deanna said that they had a couple of student calls sent in.
[SPEAKER_02]: So maybe they rearranged.
[SPEAKER_02]: So maybe she's not Mandy.
[SPEAKER_02]: I guess we better double check.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, I'll just say, I'm sorry, what is your name?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I was out observing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's
[SPEAKER_03]: Begin debrief.
[SPEAKER_02]: Come in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hello.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm really ###, huh?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's ###, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, ###.
[SPEAKER_00]: And are you really ###?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm Brian.
[SPEAKER_02]: ###.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nice to meet you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why don't you both have a seat here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm curious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you ever go by Mandy?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: No?
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, we have a different name on our sheet, so we'll make sure that we...
[SPEAKER_02]: What happened?
[SPEAKER_02]: She was sick today and wasn't able to come in.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm just filling in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: I bet that's not how you expected to start your day.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: I did this earlier.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, so this is what we call the debrief.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's a time for us to just talk about, you know, how you think that the interview and the encounter went.
[SPEAKER_02]: We've got about 15 minutes and we'll,
[SPEAKER_02]: let you do most of the talking and if there's time we can give you some of our feedback if you'd like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So and we'd like to start out with a couple questions what felt comfortable and what felt challenging.
[SPEAKER_02]: But first of all what we'd like to find out is how did you feel when you were walking down the hall knowing that you had to deliver this very bad news?
[SPEAKER_01]: Walking down the hall I was pretty nervous.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't quite know how I was going to start the conversation and that's kind of where I saw the most variability
[SPEAKER_01]: in terms of responses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so I think once I started talking, I got a little bit more comfortable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, so walking down the hall, I was fairly nervous.
[SPEAKER_02]: What did you think?
[SPEAKER_02]: What did you think that you might run into?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or how would you assess the situation once you got in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, I was thinking, you know, if it were me, I would want to know right away if there was bad news.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I also knew that I wanted to
[SPEAKER_01]: take the time to know what you understood and explain the entire situation before really saying that he had died.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so it was a little difficult for me to kind of play out the conversation in my head and know that it could play out that way instead of me walking in and saying like, oh, I'm sorry, I have bad news.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then having it go from there, it's like, oh, did he die?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then fumbling around with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And having to backtrack maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was one thing I noticed, but we can maybe talk about that in a little bit.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about you, ###?
[SPEAKER_02]: How did you feel coming down the hall knowing that you had to deal with need?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's just challenging because you know that everyone deals with grief in a different way.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so although I had done this earlier today, I knew that this experience is going to be totally different, most likely.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so it's just anticipating, like, what is this individual going to need?
[SPEAKER_02]: And what's the case?
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, the case is similar, but it's still a bit challenging.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then how are the two of us going to relay the information?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's just something that goes in my head in a way that's empathetic and helpful and comforting.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, all right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Regarding comforting, how did each of you feel about touch, level of touch, whether you should touch the person?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, I chose not to just because, um, I noticed you did a little bit and I was sitting a little bit awkwardly far away and I didn't want to like lean over and I thought it would just be a little bit too awkward to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I didn't, but it felt comfortable for you to do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It did because I felt like there was so much emotion and you know, like sometimes just a simple like touch on the shoulder,
[SPEAKER_02]: it might not be so invasive, but like, okay, you know, like I'm here and go ahead and grieve, you know?
[SPEAKER_02]: So I just, I tried to be present.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then also like, I wasn't sure like how you felt about it or if it would, if it lasted too long.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I tried to be mindful, like when your body like shifted, I was like, okay, this is my cue.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like this is enough, you know?
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It did feel okay to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: And especially when you first came in and sat next to me in this chair, rather than over in that chair,
[SPEAKER_02]: I like that too.
[SPEAKER_02]: You were really close and you had a friendly face.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I thought that was good too.
[SPEAKER_02]: So what else felt comfortable?
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously touch was okay for you today, and it may not be, I hear you saying it may not be always, you have to read the situation, but what else felt comfortable for you?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think just being present with your emotions was comfortable for me because I know like you're experiencing so much.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so sometimes when people are grieving in that way, they need someone to hold that for them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so I did feel comfortable in holding that for you, you know, when you had mentioned someone else is coming.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so I was happy to hear that, you know, that, okay, someone else is going to be here for her, but you know, we can be here for you right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that was comfortable for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I was happy, relieved also, that you were receptive to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I don't expect everyone will be, or suspect everyone will be in the future, so.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about you, ###?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, I felt more comfortable as it went along.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that, I like that
[SPEAKER_01]: I was able to offer my support in being there for you later and talking to other family members and answering questions, because I feel like that's something that I have a lot of the knowledge on, especially medically, what happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I can't imagine if I had to tell a family member that another family member had died.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so I think having sort of a professional there that knows a bit more about what happened and to speak on that makes it a lot easier for the patient and the spouse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I think so.
[SPEAKER_01]: And like when Betsy arrives, she may have questions that are specific to the doctor or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: This may seem sort of redundant or something, but how do you think important it is or how is it important to ensure that all the important friends or family members are here?
[SPEAKER_02]: Before breaking the law?
[SPEAKER_01]: This might be obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, before breaking the news.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, gosh.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's... Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's super important.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that the more people that can kind of lean on each other for support is going to make it a lot easier for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think putting sort of the pressure on whoever you're talking to to explain what happened to other members of their family is also just asking a lot of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think as many people as possible that were really close to the person who died makes it a lot easier for everybody involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me ask you, too, when you came in and you started talking about Mr. Marshall without figuring out who he was, what his relationship was to me, how did that work out for you?
[SPEAKER_02]: It was interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I never want to make assumptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so I wasn't sure where to go, and I didn't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I think that regardless of who he was to you, like if he was your brother or son, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: it wouldn't have, you know, made a difference in terms of like how I communicated because you were here and you were present for this person.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the relationship didn't necessarily change what I would have done.
[SPEAKER_02]: I wonder would it have made it easier for you then to be able to refer to him as your son or your brother or, I mean, rather than to keep saying Mr. Marshall or Jamie, his first name.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, well, I guess you did verify my name, but sometimes physicians or social workers come in and they don't even verify who I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it could be the wrong room, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: And I'm thinking, oh, well, if she didn't say my husband's name or my husband, maybe they've got the wrong room and he really is still alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I'm hoping for.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I guess I would just caution you to always address by name and verify my name and the patient's name.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just might help you, I guess, is what I'm saying, too.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is a bit of an awkward step into, you know?
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think we assume those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: We do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, like, okay, you're in room number 12 or 13, and this is the person.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're like, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know?
[SPEAKER_02]: So you're right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Verifying would be really smart to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was wondering, when you first come in, what you feel is the amount of information that you should give regarding Mr. Marshall's condition?
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Very minimal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Very minimal, could you tell?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I was like trying to not, because the thing is, if something had happened in the time between, you know, I walked from, you know, the end of the hall to the room, then I didn't want to put it, you know, on the medical student to then come in and say, well, actually, no, that's not true, you know, and then it would just be an awkward situation, you know, so I tried to be very brief and
[SPEAKER_02]: vague, and I think that that's not always the best approach, because people want answers.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, you were expecting that he was going to be okay, and... Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: But part of that, I think, ###, was based on your saying, they've got a team they're working on, they're stabilizing him, and we'll let you know what happens.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think, great, I get to take him home, he's going to be fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you said, but...
[SPEAKER_02]: they've got some cardiac they're trying to get his cardiac situation under control yeah and you know sort of like once they do that then we'll come back in so I thought oh okay things are bad but then they're good again okay so I would just caution you to be very careful about what you say and you know yeah it's got to be difficult to to have really nothing to say you can't get as much it's a fine line yeah you've got to rely on it so it's hard to
[SPEAKER_01]: to say much in terms of specific medical stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me see if there's other things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I just say something while you're looking at your notes?
[SPEAKER_02]: So tell me what felt uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_02]: I guess we talked about what felt pretty good, but other than being able to assess.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think there are a couple of things that could have done better.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was a little thrown off guard when I was washing my hands and you said, is he okay, can I take him home now?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that was probably the most uncomfortable moment and that's why I was a bit worried about the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I kinda just went from there into asking about what happened when you brought him in and then I started feeling better the more we were talking.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's something I could work on in terms of getting in, introducing myself, knowing I have bad news but working up to actually breaking the bad news.
[SPEAKER_02]: And why is that important to you?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, because I don't want to be too frank, breaking the bad news, walking in and just saying, oh, is Jamie your husband?
[SPEAKER_01]: He died.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would, I think, be worse for everybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do want to make sure that you have an understanding of what's going on, you're the right person, and that I can adequately explain what we did from our perspective and what happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so I think rushing it is not the right approach, but then there are also, you know, you can over-talk or take way too long when somebody's picking up that it's not going well and something's wrong, and you're just waiting minutes and minutes before you actually tell them what happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It also isn't ideal.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it sounds like you're saying that it gives you control over the situation if you sort of backtrack after I threw you for the loop to say, well, tell me what happened.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so it gives you a little bit more manageable or management over the situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you're in an actual situation, somebody may be really insistent, just come to the, I want to know right now, you know, did he die or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and you have to respect that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, you just have to read what's, you know, what's going to work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that is a really good approach.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've had,
[SPEAKER_01]: And students at times come in and say very quickly, Mr. Marshall died.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it didn't go well after that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I don't listen to anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: I didn't listen to anything after he was dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want that pamphlet.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't want anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just want to be with my emotions.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about you, ###?
[SPEAKER_02]: What was most uncomfortable for you?
[SPEAKER_02]: The packet.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, in the previous session, this one, I'm like, ugh.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, it's just so hard to give that to someone.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then also, like, I think trying to just make it so that it isn't so awkward.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, as you're grieving and having a difficult time, here's this giant packet of information.
[SPEAKER_02]: Please feel free to go through at your leisure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I just, it's just uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I could talk to you about it maybe the next day, just, you know, I mean, I know a lot of times people want to know, what do I do next?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I didn't get that feeling from you.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't think you were like, what do I do next?
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, it's more of like, I just need to adjust to these feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: And adjusting is not even the right term.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that was hard for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think the initial conversation too, like I really was having a hard time with what clinical information do I share?
[SPEAKER_02]: And so I completely understand your perspective of, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: you've got to be mindful of how it's conveyed because you can actually give someone hope when you're not intending to.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right, I was ready to take them home.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we probably have a minute or 30 seconds left.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's your one takeaway from this encounter?
[SPEAKER_02]: What might you do differently or the same next time?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I think I'm really going to try to, just in my head, try to keep an out for everything so that I'm prepared just in case.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, there's only seven.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a finite number of ways they can throw you off guard.
[SPEAKER_01]: One would be insisting that you tell them right away what happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if they do that multiple times, I think I would just give in and let them know from my perspective what we did and what happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then educate a little bit afterwards, even though it might be more difficult.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so it's just my approach to running it through my head before I go in the door, just so I'm prepared for everything and not going to fumble around having this very important conversation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good, good.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about you?
[SPEAKER_02]: You fumbled around a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were pretty good.
[SPEAKER_02]: I didn't notice fumbling at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you didn't fumble at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was good.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, of course, I get it that you wouldn't be prepared each time.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if it would happen for their medical, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what kind of doctor are you going to have to tell me?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm going to family medicine, so outpatient.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you might have occasion to deliver any kind of bad, not necessarily death, but
[SPEAKER_02]: a cancer diagnosis or something like that, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: What about you, ###, quickly?
[SPEAKER_02]: A takeaway.
[SPEAKER_02]: A takeaway is just that every case is different.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there are basic things that are really important.
[SPEAKER_02]: Empathy is one of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you really have to work hard to read the room a little bit because not all things can be, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: employed in the same way as individual patients.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you so much for letting us mess with you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good luck to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you have to do this again today?
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll get a lot of experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bye-bye.
Okay, are you up next?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I'm at 13.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, here you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are you doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm observing, so it's 13.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're at 13 for sure?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
Do I have time to go to the bathroom?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, I'm back at 11.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right.
All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.