[SPEAKER_02]: Go ahead and start.
[SPEAKER_04]: Come here.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hello.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi, are you Mr. Marshall's spouse?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi, I'm ###.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm the social worker working with the medical team today.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, nice to meet you.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I wanted to come in and give you an update.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: So when Mr. Marshall arrived in the emergency department today, he was having a hard time breathing.
[SPEAKER_04]: It sounds like that was happening when you called 911.
[SPEAKER_04]: And they gave him some medications to try to help his breathing.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it was still kind of getting worse.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so they placed in a breathing tube and started doing chest compressions.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what I know at this time.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I wanted to kind of give you all the information that I have.
[SPEAKER_04]: Was there anyone that you would like me to call to be with you as you wait?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, actually, my daughter Betsy is on her way here.
[SPEAKER_04]: So she should be here probably half hour, 45 minutes or so.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: So...
[SPEAKER_04]: I just got some information that the doctor is going to come and give us an update and talk with us in just a few minutes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Would you like to wait until Betsy arrives, or would you like us to speak with you before she comes?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, if she's not here, that's okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: We can go ahead and speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, excellent.
[SPEAKER_04]: And is there anything that I can get for you before I step out and talk with the doctor?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I'm good.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, excellent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_04]: We'll be right back.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Ben.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi, Mrs. Marshall.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is Dr. ###.
[SPEAKER_04]: He's been working with your husband.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: I just wanted to come in and give you the information that we have right now.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's nice to meet you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Nice to meet you as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Dr. ###, you can call me ###.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Judy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nice to meet you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So what, I know Jess had just come in and spoken with you for a little bit, so kind of tell me what you guys had spoken about.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, he just said that he was in the ER and that he was having trouble breathing and that you had to put down a breathing tube to help him breathe and that you were continuing to monitor him and would come back in and talk to me.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what happened when I met your husband.
[SPEAKER_03]: He was talking with us.
[SPEAKER_03]: He said that he had trouble breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: As you probably saw, I'm not speaking in full sentences just because it was so hard for him to catch a breath.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it sounded like the ambulance had given him a lot of breathing treatments on the way over to try to help him breathe better.
[SPEAKER_03]: And soon after I met him, his breathing got so severe that he did lose consciousness at that time.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's when we decided to help him keep breathing, to put in the breathing tube.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that we put the tube down and breathed for him.
[SPEAKER_03]: to try to move the oxygen into his body and help him on that front.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, he did put the breathing tube in.
[SPEAKER_03]: After that, just because of his continued low oxygen levels, he did go into cardiac arrest at that time.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that means that his heart stopped beating.
[SPEAKER_03]: So at that time, he immediately started CPR, chest compressions, on your husband.
[SPEAKER_03]: We had him on the monitors at all times.
[SPEAKER_03]: And he didn't have any pulses.
[SPEAKER_03]: I apologize for that.
[SPEAKER_03]: He didn't have any pulses when we checked his pulses.
[SPEAKER_03]: So he kept doing chest compressions to try to pump the blood around his body.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so he did that.
[SPEAKER_03]: We gave him some medications in an effort to try to help his heart get back to pump on its own.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it was not able to do so.
[SPEAKER_03]: We were monitoring his heart.
[SPEAKER_03]: rhythm also, and it was a rhythm that we were not able to deliver any shocks to his heart rhythm, so we kept giving chest compressions to him.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we did that for about 15 to 20 minutes or so.
[SPEAKER_03]: We kept giving chest compressions, checking if there was any pulses, and unfortunately he did not regain a pulse at that time.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I'm sorry to say that your husband has died here this afternoon.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, we've come here so many times in the past for his asthma, where you just, you know, gave him treatments and gave him medication, and we went back home, and he was fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: I knew that when he came in that second time, I should have called right then, because he was having trouble really breathing right then.
[SPEAKER_04]: I shouldn't have waited to call for EMS.
[SPEAKER_04]: I should have just put him in the car and brought him here.
[SPEAKER_04]: You did everything that you knew how to do for your husband, and you made the best decisions based on what you knew.
[SPEAKER_04]: It sounds like this was completely unexpected because he had the asthma and you brought him here before.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you did exactly what you were supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Did he suffer?
[SPEAKER_03]: Did he suffer a lot?
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't believe he suffered.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like I said, early on, before he put down the breathing tube, he did lose consciousness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I don't think he was aware of what was going on.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't think he was in any pain when we were trying to resuscitate him when he died.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm really sorry that this happened.
[SPEAKER_04]: It just doesn't seem real.
[SPEAKER_04]: I just can't believe he's gone.
[SPEAKER_04]: Jesus, what am I going to tell Betsy?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is Betsy your daughter?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: She said that she's on the way.
[SPEAKER_04]: When we can be with you, if you'd like, when we tell her, when you tell her.
[SPEAKER_04]: We want to be able to do whatever we can to support you right now.
[SPEAKER_04]: I would like that, because I'm just numb right now.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know how I could even tell her.
[SPEAKER_04]: She and her dad were so close.
[SPEAKER_04]: She's going to just be devastated.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is not what I
[SPEAKER_04]: expected what I brought in here today.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: It sounds like he's come back in the past and he did recover from those times.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: And like Jess had said, you did everything that you could, calling EMS, having him brought in, having him take the breathing treatments at home before coming in.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I cannot imagine how you're feeling right now, but I want you to know that
[SPEAKER_03]: You did the right thing to bring him in today.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I'm sorry that we were not able to bring him back this time.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: So what do we do now?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, there are some steps that we can take to give you information on how to move forward.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I want to ask first, would you like to see your husband?
[SPEAKER_04]: I would, but I want to wait until my daughter gets here to do that.
[SPEAKER_04]: We can do that together.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
Of course.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, we can do that whenever you're ready.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's no rush.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: I would prefer to wait until she gets here to do that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I better give me some time to pull myself together too.
[SPEAKER_04]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_04]: Is there anything that you can think of that we can do for you right now?
[SPEAKER_04]: Information that you would like?
[SPEAKER_04]: You know what?
[SPEAKER_04]: I can't even begin to think about all that right now.
[SPEAKER_04]: I just need to wait for Betsy to get here and then we can go and see Jamie together.
[SPEAKER_04]: Absolutely.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: What other questions do you have for us right now?
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't even know.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm sorry, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's no need to apologize.
[SPEAKER_04]: Would you like to tell us a little bit about your husband?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, he was fun-loving.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just a wonderful husband, good dad, good friend.
[SPEAKER_04]: He didn't do anything for anybody.
[SPEAKER_04]: He was always willing to help other people.
[SPEAKER_04]: And just a good person with a good heart.
[SPEAKER_04]: I guess it was just time.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was hard not to help him anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: How long were you two together?
[SPEAKER_04]: 38 years.
[SPEAKER_04]: A long time.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's incredible.
[SPEAKER_04]: You guys have a lot of good memories together.
[SPEAKER_00]: We do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sounds like both you and your daughter and all those around him love him very much.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: We do.
[SPEAKER_04]: I couldn't imagine going on without him, but I guess, you know?
[SPEAKER_04]: And you can take as much time, you know, kind of where you're at right now.
[SPEAKER_04]: It sounds like you're kind of in a place of disbelief and having a hard time thinking through all of this information.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was so unexpected.
[SPEAKER_04]: And this is, you know, an experience that many people have.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, when a loved one dies, they go through
[SPEAKER_04]: anger and shock and sadness and that disbelief and any of those experiences or other emotions are completely normal.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, I think I just need to sit for a minute and collect myself until my daughter gets here and you'll bring her back.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Would you like us to step out now?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, if I could be alone now, it would be good.
[SPEAKER_04]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_04]: Would you like a cup of water or anything?
[SPEAKER_04]: I actually have my water here, but thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right, well, we will bring Betsy back when she arrives.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you need anything at all, don't hesitate to ask us or any of the other staff members working here, and we can answer any other questions or anything that comes up before that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So don't finish.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not done, don't finish.
[SPEAKER_01]: So come on down here.
[SPEAKER_01]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, I go.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sorry, the medical students.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the social workers.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sorry about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does somebody need a writing utensil?
[SPEAKER_02]: There's some here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can we just fill this out?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can fill it out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just fill this out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
Well, they're not letting us submit.
[SPEAKER_04]: So did you have to go to the first page?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're going to have to do it on paper.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, it's your last hurrah here, so you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's true, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: I love it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're done, you can give us your form and you can go on back and talk to people.
[SPEAKER_02]: And mingle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, go into classroom three.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: 25.
[SPEAKER_02]: 25 total.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, sorry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: ###, do you want to get, or ###, or ###, do you want to get the evaluations from the social workers?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, I think.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, thanks.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cool.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, we're going to discuss it later.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in the checklist, they already fixed it with that one question.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so for the next round, they should be able to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And technically, the med student should have been able to do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But just to be safe, they're like, OK, let's wait.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, those questions are the way it does in the system.
[SPEAKER_01]: The way it does in the checklist in the system is they might have items going to the third committee,
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now my teeth are going to be all full of peanuts as I'm sucking my snack out of my teeth.
[SPEAKER_04]: You didn't talk about takeaways last time.
[SPEAKER_04]: We didn't.
[SPEAKER_04]: Actually, we didn't conclude.
[SPEAKER_04]: We ran out of time.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because she had questions and... I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, boy.
[SPEAKER_04]: Are you here Thursday, too?
[SPEAKER_00]: Hmm?
[SPEAKER_04]: Are you here Thursday?
No.
[SPEAKER_04]: What's Thursday?
[SPEAKER_04]: I can't even remember.
[SPEAKER_04]: Something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, I think it's scoring for the GFI.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think that's what it was.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: So GFA is about to come?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, they're doing it just for
[SPEAKER_04]: this one time, I think, but not, yeah, so I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: I just write the dates down.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know what I'm coming for until I look at it in the morning.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, oh, it's this one.
[SPEAKER_04]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_04]: Jim, there used to be a top one at school.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's a specific language.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I thought it was ADL.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, ADL.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Come in.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hello.
[SPEAKER_04]: How's it going?
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm Jeff.
[SPEAKER_04]: What's your name?
[SPEAKER_04]: ###.
[SPEAKER_04]: ###, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm ###.
[SPEAKER_04]: ###.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I'm ###.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was observing.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was in the other room.
[SPEAKER_04]: You didn't see me.
[SPEAKER_04]: We heard about that.
[SPEAKER_04]: All eyes on you.
[SPEAKER_04]: So now we're together.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we're going to take the next few minutes just to kind of talk about our encounter, about the next 10 or 15 minutes to talk about that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's really kind of you guys' show in terms of kind of reflection and how you think things went.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then at the end, if there's any questions for us, we're happy to answer them, and we'll also make some observations if that's okay with you guys.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, please.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so we can start with, we'll start with Jez, since he came in first.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's all right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, I definitely, you know, like, was noticing my own kind of experience first, like very much adrenaline, and before I came into the room, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: making sure to take deep breaths because I wanted to come in and approach you with like a kind of a more relaxed body language more calm state and definitely like felt like you know I gave you some information but when we came back in with ### like it like I was like oh maybe all the information that I had communicated didn't necessarily necessarily like I didn't communicate it clearly to you
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, I felt like, well, let's just say this, now that you brought that up, I think that your role was not to go into a lot of detail, but just kind of give me an update, and I felt like you handled that.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, did you, ###?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I didn't.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because I think there are certain things that the physician needs to do, and I think you sort of, I think you did a great job setting the stage that things have not gone well.
[SPEAKER_04]: as we might have hoped.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I think that was probably pretty helpful to you to know that, oh, this is not... Right, it was.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it didn't prepare me for what I was about to hear, but at least it let me know that there were things that were not going so well, but they were being worked on and they were being attended to.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that gave me a sense of relief that even though it wasn't great, he was being well taken care of.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's, at this point, I think all you could do in terms of reassuring me
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and then when we came back in together, you know, I really wanted to make sure that we worked well as a team and gave you the information that you wanted, but also offered you support.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sometimes what I feel like I can do is ask, like, what do you need?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or how can I support you?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, too many times when you're really overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I was really...
[SPEAKER_04]: happy because i know how hard this can be for me which is to like sit in silence and let you kind of process as much as you needed and gauge the information that you were able to take you know they gave us the packet the bereavement packet but you know when i asked you like what what do you want to know about what comes next you know what i heard was like
[SPEAKER_04]: I want my daughter to come.
[SPEAKER_04]: We want to see my husband.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I was like, okay, not in a time to give this information.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that was completely appropriate for you to do that, to have that kind of response.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because I was letting you know, I can't even deal with that right now.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, you know, for you to have gone on and insisted that we talk about those things would have been inappropriate in that setting.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you read that cue very well and just kind of backed off.
[SPEAKER_04]: At least you made me aware that it's there and that you would,
[SPEAKER_04]: But we're available to discuss it with me at a later time.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: How do you think things went?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is there anything that was challenging or comfortable?
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't think comfortable.
[SPEAKER_03]: I didn't think it was going to be comfortable.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's possible.
[SPEAKER_04]: At least uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_03]: At least uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_03]: I really felt like ### and I worked well together in terms of kind of going back and forth in terms of the support mechanisms and asking if you needed assistance or
[SPEAKER_03]: kind of feeling out where you were and then I tried to kind of give them more medical narrative of what happened kind of the more objective steps along the along the way right so I think that that was one of the things that went went well and kind of one of the things I also struggle with is silence and I feel like I did a better though if never perfect job of like allowing you to kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: answer questions and then, you know, I would leave a couple more seconds and then you'd be able, you'd add on like another sentence or another kind of thought to the end of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I'm allowing you to complete thoughts without feeling like I was jumping into the next step and try not to make you feel like it was a rushed interaction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Make you feel like you were able to kind of say everything that you needed to say.
[SPEAKER_03]: Those are the good things.
[SPEAKER_03]: The bad things, my page went off.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was mad about that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I tried to like gloss over it so it wasn't.
[SPEAKER_04]: You handled that very well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I'm glad to hear that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I was like, I knew it was going to happen.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I should have been prepared.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yes, but that was one thing that I just, I knew just like had to wait, whatever it was, that this is more important.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then I think it's just challenging sometimes when you're giving that medical narrative to, I always try to speak in more lay terms, but sometimes I feel like I don't pause enough along the way.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, it was, like, the series of events that happens, like, he, like, pulse was lost, then went into cardiac arrest, then chest compressions.
[SPEAKER_03]: I feel like the way I said that was not jargony, but was just, like, it just kind of went on and on to try to get, and, like, I finally took a breath when I said that he died.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was, like, I was trying to, like, lead you, like, lead up, lead up, lead up, and then I, like, and then he died.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then I was, like, I felt like I was, like, unloading that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know how I did that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you know, I feel that it's better to do it that way.
[SPEAKER_04]: To not just come in the room and say, he's dead.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was with him in the ER and now he's dead.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, so it gives me some time to listen to what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because if you just tell me he's dead, I'm not hearing anything else that you're saying after that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Plus, it also gives me a sense of reassurance
[SPEAKER_04]: that everything that could have been done was done to save him.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you know, I think that you could go into a lot more medical terms, and you didn't.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the couple that you did, you did explain what they were, and so that's fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: So keeping it as lay as possible is good, but at the same time you want to give enough information so that the person knows that they really had been given
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, good treatment and well taken care of while they were there.
[SPEAKER_04]: You mentioned telling the story or, you know, giving me a chance, time to give me a chance to comment in between.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you think that when you came in that you gave me the opportunity to tell the story, my story?
[SPEAKER_03]: If not, or if so, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: If not, why?
[SPEAKER_03]: I didn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: I wanted to ask me kind of what you knew, because I knew that Jaz had shared with you kind of what led up to now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Later on in the conversations where we, when you kind of said, when you expressed your own guilt about, did I call early enough?
[SPEAKER_03]: That was the first time I got like the pre-hospital story.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I tried, and so maybe I could have done a better job of soliciting kind of what happened today versus what do you know happened in the hospital.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I tried to
[SPEAKER_03]: come to kind of where you were in terms of the progression of events while, since I guess I met him in the emergency room, till I guess where Jas left off in terms of what he saw in the emergency room.
[SPEAKER_04]: Neither way is wrong or right.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just a matter of allowing, perhaps first allowing me to tell you what happened before we got here.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that way I can get that out, and then I can listen to what you have to say.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I think that...
[SPEAKER_04]: What do you think the benefit would have been if she had told you what had happened this morning?
[SPEAKER_03]: I think it would have given me more context into what she felt.
[SPEAKER_03]: As we were talking more, I could tell that there was an underlying guilt of, did I do enough myself?
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think if I elicited that earlier, I may have been more prepared for that kind of reaction to his death, that she took some of the blame for it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas I kind of got there, but a little bit indirectly.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think we could have gauged, too, how unexpected this was.
[SPEAKER_04]: One of us had asked that question.
[SPEAKER_04]: I also, thinking about you, said this was a really stressful situation, so I pulled myself together out here before I came in.
[SPEAKER_04]: It might have been helpful had she been able to tell her story for you to be able to get your wits about you.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, it gives you a chance to sort of
[SPEAKER_04]: settle in, and then you begin to have a conversation rather than you being the one doing all the talking.
[SPEAKER_04]: Does that seem to have some value to it?
[SPEAKER_04]: That was the only thing that I... Do you have more that you want to say?
[SPEAKER_04]: The gesturing or the touch.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, some people like to be touched, some people don't like to be touched.
[SPEAKER_04]: In this situation, you never know.
[SPEAKER_04]: You just kind of have to read the patient.
[SPEAKER_04]: But at the same time, if you're not comfortable doing it, I'm going to feel that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you're not sure, compassion and empathy can be expressed in other ways other than touch.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can express it in the words that you use, in the tone in your voice.
[SPEAKER_04]: you know, and the gesture of what you did of just putting the tis### there.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, to me, that level of touch doesn't necessarily mean that you're not displaying empathy or compassion.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, you're doing that by your demeanor to me, so that to me, that's just as important.
[SPEAKER_04]: Did you feel like you got that from?
[SPEAKER_04]: I did.
[SPEAKER_04]: I felt like I got it from both of you.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think that you both displayed genuineness, you know, and some compassion and empathy when you were talking to me.
[SPEAKER_04]: You gave me time.
[SPEAKER_04]: You
[SPEAKER_04]: explained enough to me.
[SPEAKER_04]: You made sure that I was comfortable with knowing exactly what had transpired.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so I did feel very comfortable.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think that the two of you worked well together, like you said.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, you both had input.
[SPEAKER_04]: Five minutes remaining.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so I think that went well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you have anything else?
[SPEAKER_04]: Just the one thing that we were talking about, and we've done this a fair number of times, was that nobody has ever said, tell me about your husband.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the first time.
[SPEAKER_04]: It took me a minute.
[SPEAKER_04]: And as I was observing this, I thought, oh man, if he'd said that, I would have absolutely dissolved into tears.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it was such a competitive... I mean, he's a human being.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we both thought that that... I mean, we were shocked that nobody had ever said that before, but it was also a very humanizing... He really was...
[SPEAKER_04]: person, and he is, and that, just how shocking it was.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it was very shocking.
[SPEAKER_04]: I've never had that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But at the same time, I felt like it was a good deflection for a minute.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because I could then start to think about, even though I'm still devastated by his loss, I could still think about all the wonderful experiences we had, and the marriage, and children, and all those things, which would be very comforting.
[SPEAKER_04]: at a time like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's something you should keep in your wheelhouse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, and I think, yeah, like what, like when my thing was, it's like, you know, we're sitting here and we're, we're thinking about him and we're thinking about him in a particular way, but you know, I, I want to learn from you how, how you're feeling, but also you're feeling about him and kind of rememb###g, yeah, that, that holistic person.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that was good for me.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that would be good for a spouse to really think about, even though this is really sad.
[SPEAKER_04]: Let's think about who he was and what he meant to you and the kind of person he was.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that would be comforting to somebody.
[SPEAKER_04]: Any questions for us?
[SPEAKER_04]: I was going to say, I'm concerned about the time.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I wanted to go over the things we've talked about.
[SPEAKER_04]: We've talked about silence.
[SPEAKER_04]: We've talked about being able to tell your story.
[SPEAKER_04]: And we talked about touch.
[SPEAKER_04]: silence, being a human being.
[SPEAKER_04]: So there are things you're going to take away from this that next time around, because there will be more bad news.
[SPEAKER_04]: It may not be this, but there will be bad news that you want to think about when you're having to deliver bad news.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think the biggest thing is to just kind of sit down, just not only just to be at the same level as whoever you're speaking with, patient or family member, but just to kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: bring yourself into the moment and kind of take a deep breath and center yourself to really get you into that mindset and you don't feel like you're just like walking by and then like saying something you actually like sit down and try to get into as possible and sometimes it's harder than others to get into a possible situation or comfortable situation yeah I would agree in terms of being present and very intentional and you know being able to making sure that I'm like taking stock of what's happening so that I
[SPEAKER_04]: know I can keep that in check while relaying and doing what I need to do to support you or the patient.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because I know, like, in the past when I've had to give bad news, sometimes I feel like I get so nervous and frenzied and anxious that, like, that can really come off to other people.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so making sure that, like, that's not your responsibility to manage my feelings at all.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's good that you, like you said, you take a deep breath before you go in.
[SPEAKER_04]: Kind of center yourself, you know.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's not easy.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's never easy.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's especially not easy when it's not expected.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, if it's a long-term illness and you know what the end result is going to be.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even though it's difficult, it's a little bit easier to take.
[SPEAKER_04]: But when it's completely unexpected, you know, then it...
[SPEAKER_04]: can really blow somebody away, and making sure that they don't feel the guilt, because that can set the whole tone, you know, for the rest of their lives, you know, if you don't assure them that what they did was, you know.
[SPEAKER_04]: Questions for us?
[SPEAKER_04]: Anything you said or did that you wondered about, how did it come about?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, like one takeaway of something to improve upon.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's a hard one.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because honestly, you guys both did a good job.
[SPEAKER_04]: The only thing that I think about is a chance to tell her story.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that it's the two of us in this together rather than, because I think you get so much from her being, and she certainly does, that this is so unexpected.
[SPEAKER_04]: So let me tell you.
[SPEAKER_04]: what happened to me this morning.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you so much for volunte###g to be our patient.
[SPEAKER_04]: No problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's our pleasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: We've been doing it a long time.
I know, and I was like, oh, okay.
So go about your business.
Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: How much time do we have?
[SPEAKER_02]: One minute.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
Thank you.
Yeah, I think it's her stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think this is her stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where is she?
[SPEAKER_02]: Right there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Does she need to go with her cohort?
Oh.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, they're just gabbing.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're just talking.
Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think the one thing I